Guide to the James Buell Munn Collection 1873-1980 MC 2 MC.2
New York University Archives
James Buell Munn Papers
1873-1980
New York University Archives
Munn, James Buell, 1890-1967
Munn, Ruth Crosby Hanford
MC.2
13 Linear Feet in 13 boxes
James Buell Munn served as an educator and administrator at New York University during the years 1920 and 1932. His father, John Pixley Munn (1846-1931), a physician, was a member of the University's governing council from 1892 until his death in 1931, and was a major financial benefactor. Munn's mother, Martha Buell Plum Munn (1856-1926), was active in the Woman's Advisory Committee of the School of Education, and the Woman's Law Class. Munn's sister, Aristine Munn-Recht, became a practicing physician and was the first Dean of Women at Washington Square in 1917. The Munn estate papers consist of correspondence, reports, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, biographical and genealogical data, diaries, photographs, printed matter, and ephemera relating to Munn's tenure at Washington Square College, 1920-1932, and his continuing relationship with the college and his former students. There is also material relating to the family's various endeavors, including: Munn's father's medical career in New York, Munn's mother's work with the Woman's Advisory Committee and the Woman's Law Class, and the Munn family farm records.
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
The Administrative Papers of the Chancellor Henry Mitchell MacCracken
The New York University Woman's Law Class Records
The Personal Papers of Elmer Ellsworth Brown
The Administrative Papers of Chancellor Elmer Ellsworth Brown
The Harry Woodburn Chase Papers
Arrangement
Consists of the James Buell Munn Estate Collection and the James Buell Munn Memorial Collection and is arranged into 12 series. The Estate collection is arranged as follows: Series I - Family; Series II - James Buell Munn; Series III -The James Buell Munn Scholarship Fund; Series IV -Miscellaneous; Series V -Photographs/Artifacts. The Memorial Collection is arranged as follows; Series I -Acquisition; Series II -Munn Correspondence; Series III -Memoirs; Series IV -Photographs; Series V -Publications -Munn Students; Series VI -Materials derived from the New York University Archives; Series VII -James Buell Munn Exhibit, May-September, 1980.
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading within each series.
Scope and Content Note
The James Buell Munn Papers in the New York University Archives consist of materials relevant to Munn's tenure at Washington Square College (1920-1932) and his continuing relationship with New York University after his resignation in February, 1932 (to accept a post in the Harvard University English Department) until his death in 1967. There are also materials related to Munn's family and copies of records and diaries that date from his student days at Harvard University.
Munn's papers came under the trusteeship of his wife, Ruth Crosby Hanford Munn, in 1967. In 1975 she removed them from Cambridge to the family farm in Scottsboro, New York, where, with the assistance of Jacob D. Goldstein, a former Washington Square College student and Munn family friend, Mrs. Munn sorted the material into family-related, Harvard-related, and New York University-related categories. When Mrs. Munn died in August, 1976, Jacob D. Goldstein completed the sorting. As Mrs. Munn desired, the family related materials were deposited in the Rush Rhees Library at the University of Rochester, the Harvard-related materials were deposited in the Harvard University Archives, and the New York University-related materials were deposited in the New York University Archives during the Fall of 1978 and Spring of 1979.
The collection illustrates Munn's significance to the development of Washington Square College during the 1920's, and is a repository of materials that testify to the unique and enduring relationship that Munn established with his students.
The James Buell Munn Papers in the New York University Archives consist of the James Buell Munn Estate Collection, the materials preserved by Mrs. Munn, and the James Buell Munn Memorial Collection, which was established in the Fall of 1978 in honor of Munn's significant work at Washington Square College.
The James Buell Munn Estate Collection consists of papers and photographs that date from 1873-1979. It has been arranged in five series:
Series I (1873-1926) consists of materials that relate to Munn's family: his grandfather (Edwin G. Munn), his father (John Pixley Munn) and mother (Martha Buell Plum Munn), and a few items related to Munn's sister and her husband (Aristine Pixley Munn-Recht and Charles Recht), Munn's maternal grandmother (Martha Buell Plum), and cousins Fannie Munn Field and John Munn Hanford, M.D. The materials that relate to Munn's family include genealogies for both the Munn, Pixley, and Buell families (the genealogical materials trace the Pixley and Munn families from 1620 and 1637 respectively; the pages from the Buell family Bible trace the Buell family back to 1794); biographical data; correspondences printed materials, and newspaper clippings relative to Edwin G. Munn's successful medical practice near Rochester John Pixley Munn's settlement and success as a doctor and businessman in New York City; letters from John Pixley to James Buell Munn at Harvard and during the summer of 1926 that reflect the warm relationship between the father and son; Mrs. John Pixley Munn's work as a member of the New York University Woman's Advisory Committee and her participation in the Woman's Law Class, and her estate. There is also some correspondence to Munn from Fannie Munn Field (cousin who administered the Munn family farm) and John Munn Hanford, M.D. (who provided medical services for Munn's students who stayed at the farm). These materials constitute a background for the extensive James Buell Munn materials.
Series II (1891-1975) consists of materials that relate to Munn and his wife, Ruth Crosby Hanford Munn* There are correspondence, reports, writings by Munn, printed materials, and newspaper clippings that document Munn's experiences as a young man at Harvard University, his continuing relationship with Harvard after his graduation in 1912 through his acceptance of a teaching post in the Harvard English Department in 1932, his decision in 1919 to remain in New York City and acceptance of a teaching post in the English Department at Washington Square College, his work at and significance to Washington Square College during his tenure there, and his continuing relationship with New York University after his resignation in 1932 until his death in 1967. Because of Munn's role at Washington Square College, the collection reflects the growth of the College during the 1920's and student life there during those years. Of particular significance is the correspondence between Munn and his "boys," which began in 1923 and continued until his death. The correspondence illustrates the early and continuing interest and support Munn gave to this exceptional group of students. The "Munn Students" correspondence also contains letters from former Washington Square College students who were not directly aided by Munn. Their letters, written years after graduation, are tributes to Munn's significant role at the College.
The papers of Ruth Crosby Hanford Munn consist of correspondence with Munn and former colleagues and students, and correspondence and newspaper clippings relating to her gift of Munn's library to the Boston Public Library in 1968.
Series III (1962-1979) consists of correspondence, contributor lists, and reports related to the James Buell Munn Scholarship Fund, established in 1963 at New York University by Munn's former students.
Series IV contains miscellaneous materials. It consists of a folder containing inventories of the Munn Estate Collection materials deposited in the University Archives in the Fall of 1978 by Jacob D. Goldstein.
Series V consists of photographs of the Munn family and associates, and of the "Munn Students" at the Munn farm. Most of the photographs are not dated. The family photographs include Munn's maternal grandmother, Martha Maria Buell Plum, his mother and father, Munn and his sister Aristine as children and young adults, and Aristine's husband Charles Recht. Photographs of Munn family associates include the Rev. George Alexander, Helen M. Gould, a group photograph of the Munn and McCracken families at the Heights campus of New York University, Homer A. Watt in 1947, and photographs of Fannie Munn Field and the "Munn Students" at the Munn farm, 1923-1926. This series also contains a silver cup given to Fannie Munn Field by the "Munn Students" in 1924.
The James Buell Munn Memorial Collection was begun during the negotiations between Bayrd Still, Director, Archives Office, and Jacob D. Goldstein that resulted in the deposit of the Estate Collection in the New York University Archives. In October, 1978, it was decided to augment the materials in the Estate Collection by soliciting extant Munn letters and memoirs from former students. A fund was established by three former students to arrange the Estate Collection and acquire Munn letters and other material that may have been preserved by his former students.
The materials in the Memorial Collection have been arranged in seven series. Series I (1952-1979) contains folders relating to the acquisition of the Estate Collection and the commencement of the Memorial Collection, including correspondence, mailing lists, and financial data. Folder 5 contains current correspondence relating to the acquisition of the Memorial Collection materials. Folder 6 contains printed materials about Munn's students. Series II (1923-1948) contains letters received from Munn that have been contributed by his former students. Series III (1976-1979) contains memoirs written by former students and colleagues. Series IV contains photographs received from former students.*
The James Buell Munn Memorial Collection has been expanded since the original accession date. Three series have been added: Series V contains publications of several of Munn's former students. Series VI contains correspondence and photographs derived from the New York University Archives. Series VII contains the materials used to develop the James Buell Munn Exhibit and photographs of the exhibit.
The Estate Collection is complete as constituted. The Memorial Collection has been organized as the repository for all materials received as the result of solicitation of Munn's former students.
The Estate Collection (with the exception of Series V: Photographs/Artifact) is located in one drawer; the Memorial Collection occupies approximately three quarters of a foot of a second drawer; Series V/Estate Collection is located in a third drawer (drawers 55-57).
The following are among the correspondents in the James Buell Munn Papers:
George Alexander
A. A. Beaumont
Arthur Beane
A. L. Bouton
Elmer E. Brown
James Buchman
Paul H. Buck
Miguel de Capriles
Oscar Cargill
Henry A. Chairpper
Harry Woodburn Chase
Henry Sloan Coffin
Chauncy M. Depew
Benjamin T. Fairchild
Erwin N. Griswold
James M. Hester
Henry James
John Livingston Jones
Fred I. Kent
Fiske Kimball
LeRoy Kimball
Delmar Leighton
Alfred L. Mannhardt
Frank H. McClosky
John Musser
Charles C. Pollock
Roscoe Pound
David Sarnoff
Harlow Shapley
Percy S. Strauss
Randall Thompson
John Roscoe Turner
Harold O. Voorhis
Winthrop W. Wade
Homer A. Watt
Series Outline
The James Buell Munn Estate Collection
Series I - Family
Subseries A -Edwin George Munn (JBM's grandfather)
Subseries B -John Pixley Munn (JBM's father)
Subseries C -Martha Buell Plum Munn (JBM's mother)
Subseries D - Other Family
Series II - James Buell Munn
Subseries A -Biographical Data
Subseries B -Harvard University
Subseries C -New York University
Subseries D -Munn Farm
Subseries E -Organizations
Subseries F -Appointment Books
Subseries G -Writings
Subseries H -Legal Papers
Subseries I - Newspaper Clippings
Subseries J -Ruth Crosby Hanford Munn
Series III -The James Buell Munn Scholarship Fund
Series IV -Miscellaneous
Series V -Photographs/Artifacts
Subseries A -Photographs/Family
Subseries B -Photographs/Associates
Subseries C -Photographs/Munn Farm
Subseries D -Artifact/Munn Farm
The James Buell Munn Memorial Collection
Series I -Acquisition (Munn Estate and Memorial Collections)
Series II -Munn Correspondence
Series III -Memoirs
Series IV -Photographs
*Series added to the Memorial Collection, Winter, 1980-1981:
Series V -Publications -Munn Students
Series VI -Materials derived from the New York University Archives
Series VII -James Buell Munn Exhibit, May-September, 1980
Historical/Biographical Note
James Buell Munn (September 24, 1890 - February 13, 1967) came to Washington Square College in February, 1920, as an English instructor. When he resigned in February, 1932, to accept a position in the Harvard University English Department, he was Dean of the College. During this period Munn served as director of the Washington Square College Section of the Extramural Division (1922-23) and director of the Evening Division (1923-24). He became Assistant Dean of the College in 1925 and Dean in 1928. During his twelve years at Washington Square College, Munn established himself as an inspiring teacher and highly respected colleague who left a significant legacy of educational and personal service beyond his day-to-day duties. He improved the library, laboratory and student facilities through anonymous donations, and was responsible (anonymously) for the education of a significant number of young men (and a few women) who would otherwise not have been able to achieve a college education. Many of these students later became successful writers, poets, professional and businessmen. A large group were close to Munn during their student years and were given the use of the library at his 58th Street home, evenings at the Metropolitan Opera and Carnegie Hall, summers at the Munn family farm near Rochester, New York, and financial help for needed clothing and books. The correspondence between Munn and the "Munn Students" illustrates the close, supportive relationship Munn established with these students. Munn's popularity also extended throughout the student body, and in 1925 the Washington Square College yearbook, Album, was dedicated to him.
The Collection documents Munn's commitment that Washington Square College serve the New York City community by providing both the traditional collegiate education and necessary pre-professional training of its students, who, in the main, were derived from an immigrant population that wanted to educate its children while keeping them close to home. Munn interpreted the College's role to be the provision of traditional educational experiences, and preparation for personal and vocational success in the American environment.
Munn's work with students is illustrative of his family's beneficence. Munn's grandfather, Edwin G. Munn (April 7, 1804-December 12, 1847), was a pioneer in the field of ophthalmology, who carried on a successful medical practice in Scottsboro, New York. He became known throughout western New York for excellent medical care, and for paying the passage and medical treatment for those who could not afford it. His wife, Aristine Pixley Munn, donated land for the Woman's College at the University of Rochester. Edwin G. Munn's office records and medical library have been deposited at the University of Rochester.
Munn's father, John Pixley Munn (December 11, 1846-August 15, 1931), carried on a successful medical practice in New York City. He was personal physician to Russell Sage and Jay Gould* Starting out as medical examiner of the United States Life Insurance Company of New York City, he eventually became the company's president, and served on the boards of directors of several railroads and banking houses. He was a trustee at New York University from 1892 until his death in 1931, and ex-officio treasurer of the Woman's Advisory Committee (established in 1890 when women were first admitted to the University's School of Pedagogy). As a member of the University Council, John Pixley Munn was instrumental in the merger between his alma mater, the Bellevue Hospital Medical College, with the University Medical School in May, 1898, and a gift from him to the University in 1925 helped construct a temporary twelve-story building for the School of Education (completed in 1930) until a larger, permanent building could be financed. John Pixley Munn also served as a trustee at the University of Rochester from 1886 until 1931; he was president of the Board during most of these years.
Munn's mother, Martha Buell Plum Munn (August 2, 1856-September 13, 1926), served New York University as treasurer of the Woman's Advisory Committee and president of the Woman's Legal Education Society (which administered the Woman's Law Class (established in 1890 to present lectures on law for women under the University's sponsorship). Mrs. Munn worked closely in these endeavors with Mrs. Russell Sage and Helen M. Gould, and lectured to women's classes in finance and law. In 1918 she established the Woman's Law Class Gown Fund to provide for repair and replacement of graduation gowns. Mrs. Munn also established several scholarship funds at New York University in honor of William A. Wheelock (former Council member, $450), the Rev. George Alexander (minister of The First Presbyterian Church of New York City and Munn family friend, $450) and James Buell (Mrs. Munn's grandfather, $4,500). In 1914 Mrs. Munn gave the University a $300 gift that was used for repairs in Main Building. Mrs. Russell Sage established a $500 scholarship fund in honor of Mrs. Munn. Mrs. Munn's daughter, Aristine Pixley Munn-Recht, served as Washington Square College's first Dean of Women from 1917 until the early 1920's. The papers of John Pixley and Martha Buell Plum Munn have been deposited at the Rush Rhees Library, University of Rochester.
Munn's interest in New York University did not end with his resignation from Washington Square College in 1932. Although he remained at Harvard for 25 years until his retirement in 1957, he maintained contact with his former colleagues and students. Ruth Crosby Hanford Munn, whom Munn married in 1932, also corresponded with Munn's former colleagues and students until her death in August, 1976. In 1945 New York University awarded Munn an Honorary Degree. In 1963 his former students established the James Buell Munn Scholarship Fund.
Appendix
For references to James Buell Munn in the New York University Archives, please see Card Catalog under MUNN, J.B.
References include:
Recollections of former faculty and students
References to Munn in oral history interviews conducted by Bayrd Still
Elmer E. Brown Papers
Jacob Fisher's autobiographical memoir of student life at Washington Square College during the 1920's (On Vanishing Ground, 1979).
Further references to Munn in the New York University Archives include:
Harry Woodburn Chase Papers
Washington Square Yearbook, Album, for the years 1921-1932 (including pictures of Munn and his students)
Report of the Dean of Washington Square College by Munn in New York University: Reports of Officers to Chancellor, for the years 1927-1928; 1928-1929; 1929-1930; 1930-1931
Department of Fine Arts, Excerpts from Minutes of Board of Trustees, 1927-1930
Published Writings by Munn include:
Blum, David L, Some Recent New York University Verse, New York: New York University Press, 1926; see "Introduction." (copy in NYU Archives)
Jones, Theodore Francis, ed., New York University: 1832-1932, New York: New York University Press, 1933; See chapter "The Washington Square College."
Munn, J.B. and Watt, H.A., Ideas & Forms in English and American Literature, Chicago, Atlanta, Dallas, New York: Scott Foresman & Co., 1925, 1932.
References to Martha Buell Plum Munn in the New York University Archives include:
H. M. McCracken Papers
Washington Square College yearbook, Album, 1923, p. 213 (includes picture).
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Provenance
This collection was donated by Ruth Crosby Hanford Munn and Jacob D. Goldstein in 1978 and 1979.
Law |x Study and teaching.; Correspondence.; Education -- Study and teaching.; Universities and Colleges -- Administration; Scholarships.; Biographies.; Munn farm (Rochester, N.Y.); Diaries; photoprints.; Munn family; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science; Munn, Edwin; Munn, John Pixley, 1846-1931; Harvard University; Munn, Martha Buell, 1856-1926; Munn, Ruth Crosby Hanford; Munn-Recht, Aristine; Alexander, George, 1843-1930; Buell Family; Gould, Helen Miller; James Buell Munn Scholarship Fund; New York University; New York University. Women's Advisory Committee; MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1840-1918; New York University. Woman's Law Class; Washington Square College. English Dept
- Series I: Family
  - Subseries A: Edwin George Munn
    - Biographical Data Handwritten reminiscence; article in Buffalo Medical Journal by C. W. Hennington; short biographical sketch., 1894, 1912, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence Letter from Rochester railroad office re patient (xerox)., 1840 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Buffalo Medical Journal, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Article on Edwin Munn's Papers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries B: John Pixley Munn
    - Biographical Data Listed as medical student in Annual Circular, Bellevue Hospital Medical College, p. 14; Who's Who in Finance & Banking; short biographical sketch., 1873-1902, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Biographical Data; Story of a Bookman, H. Robinson Shipherd References to JPM's assistance when Shipherd was a student at Harvard University, pp. 27-29. Genealogy Materials that trace the descent of the Munn family from Benjamin Munn in 1637, and the Pixley family from Governor William Bradford, 1620. Correspondence (May 1, 1879-Sept. 28, 1926) Includes letter of reference from Chauncy M. Depew; letters from JPM to his son James Buell., 1955, 1879-1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - Duplicates Xerox copies of letters from JPM to James Buell., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Organizations Membership certificate to the Medical Association of the Greater City of New York., 1900 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings Described as physician and friend of Jay Gould, Russell Sage; United States Life Insurance Company of New York scandal., 1892-1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Clippings - Associates Obituary of Mrs. H. R. Shipherd., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries C: Martha Buell Plum Munn
    - Biographical Data Death Certificate (Sept. 13, 1926) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biographical Data Obituary (xerox), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Genealogy Record kept in Buell family Bible includes entries from 1794-1899 of births, marriages, and deaths. (xerox), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - New York University - Woman's Advisory Committee Minutes, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - New York University - Woman's Law Class Invitations to Opening Exercises., 1897-1903 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - New York University - Woman's Law Class Copies of "Bi-weekly Bulletin" (4)., 1901-1904 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - New York University Woman's Law Class Lecture (transcript) given by Mrs. Munn, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - New York University - Woman's Law Class "For The Better Protection of Their Rights," pamphlet written to celebrate 50th anniversary of the Woman's Law Class; references to Mrs. Munn, pp. 40-41, 51-52., 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)